<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://house.youngram.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://house.youngram.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-21T21:25:01-06:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Youngram House Journal</title><subtitle>Chronicling our homeowner journey</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to plan a garden, part two: the details</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/how-to-plan-a-garden-part-two.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to plan a garden, part two: the details" /><published>2021-02-21T20:34:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-21T20:34:00-06:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/how-to-plan-a-garden-part-two</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/how-to-plan-a-garden-part-two.html">&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-plan-a-garden-part-one.html&quot;&gt;journey thus far&lt;/a&gt; in landscape design had arrived at a high-level plan for the yard that split it into segments with themes driving the design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/general-plan-1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of our lot with themed areas marked&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/general-plan-480.png 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/general-plan-800.png 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/general-plan-1200.png 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/general-plan.png 1456w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an excellent starting point for the design, but I still had to fill in a lot of details and figure out what we were actually going to put in, and where.
I already extolled the virtues of &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chelseagreen.com/product/edible-forest-gardens-volume-ii/&quot;&gt;Edible Forest Gardens, Volume Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; in the previous post, so I’ll spare you more of that, but suffice it to say that I learned a lot about the following planning steps from it as well, from broad concepts down to specific advice on drafting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-map-of-the-territory&quot;&gt;A map of the territory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve shown you an overview map of our lot that I used for high-level planning, but let’s back up and talk about how I got that map in the first place.
We didn’t have any documents to use as a starting point, so it was up to me to come up with a decently accurate map of the yard and existing features.
Here’s my working document:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/overview-map-sketch-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A very rough sketch of our lot layout&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/overview-map-sketch-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/overview-map-sketch-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/overview-map-sketch-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/overview-map-sketch.jpg 1917w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sketched out the house and yard and then spent a while walking around outside measuring every component you see marked on there.
For the longer segments, I marked out about 40 feet with masking tape on a spool of rope I had found abandoned in the garage and used that with a little stake to hold one end.
This let me measure large distances like the sides of the lot fairly quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my annotated sketch in hand, I was ready to get out graph paper and start putting together an accurately-scaled drawing of the lot.
You can see I didn’t measure every dimension of every feature, but rather just enough of the dimensions that the other ones can be deduced with the existing information.
Were our lot bigger or more complicated, I might have needed to use fancier techniques like triangulation to accurately locate some features, but on my map that never felt necessary.
Most features were easily placed with right angles, and I only needed it to be accurate within a couple feet anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/overview-map-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A finished map of our whole lot layout&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/overview-map-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/overview-map-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/overview-map-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/overview-map.jpg 1375w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This final map was drawn on 10x10 graph paper.
I have another version drawn in Sketchup, which is the one you see in the previous post, but I didn’t end up using that version much during the planning process.
The graph paper version was easier to refer back to, as I could easily count out measurements of an area I was interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools-of-the-trade&quot;&gt;Tools of the trade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In preparation for doing a lot of mapping, I assembled some tools to help.
These weren’t all necessary, but they did make the job a bit faster and more pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Graph paper&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I got two types, 10 squares per inch and 4 squares per inch. The 10x10 is easiest to do math with, and matches up with the common engineer's scale of 1:10.
      It's a good size for larger maps but was a little too small for doing finer designs on specific areas, like mapping out exact plant locations.
      The 4x4 graph paper was a much better scale for those drawings.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Tracing paper&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Once I had a map drawn, I could quickly trace the boundaries onto tracing paper to make copies.
      This was handy when I wanted to try out different potential layouts or iterate several times on a design.
      There are other ways I could have dealt with this, so the tracing paper was not a necessity, but it did come in handy a few times.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000KIDVJE/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o06_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Circle drawing template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I stumbled on this by chance but it turned out to be one of the most useful tools I picked up.
      This particular template has a wide range of circle sizes that were perfect for drawing trees, bushes, and forbs.
      It's much easier and faster to draw small circles this way than with a compass, and much neater than trying to draw circles freehand.
      There are other templates with a variety of architectural shapes, but circles was all I ever needed.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Compass&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Purchased to make circles, but the circle drawing template picked up most of the work so I didn't use this much.
      Still a useful tool to have around, and has a few uses in addition to circles, such as quickly transferring distances.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Engineer's triangular scale&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Like an ordinary Imperial ruler, but with inches broken into fractions of 10 rather than 12.
      Used with 1:10 graph paper, you can make measurements that translate to feet with no conversion required.
      While it seemed like a great idea, I didn't end up using this very much.
      If I weren't primarily working on graph paper, or if our site were bigger and had fewer right angles, I might have needed it more often.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000JQSV7E/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o00_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Clutch pencil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Not a necessary purchase, but a nice complement to mechanical pencils.
      Has a wider expressive range, such as drawing thicker lines, or shading areas.
      Sturdy and will last me forever.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lay-of-the-land&quot;&gt;The lay of the land&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elevation changes are typically an important part of site design.
The contours of a site can affect water drainage, microclimates, ease of access, and so on.
I won’t be discussing this much, for the simple reason that our lot doesn’t have any elevation changes.
It’s graded completely flat and is level with the sidewalk, so we don’t even have the small front yard hill that many South Minneapolis lots do.
For the most part, this was fine, as it made my job easier.
I thought a few times about adding mounds or hills to provide some variety, but there was nowhere in the yard that seemed like it would particularly benefit from that, and since the drainage on our site is generally fine, I was hesitant to make any changes that would throw things out of balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important thing to consider early in the design process is hardscaping.
In our case, this was also fairly easy.
There is a small patio behind the house, and if we ever decide to add a larger patio, it will go in that same area.
I don’t have any plans to change the location of the other sidewalks, and other than slightly decreasing the size of the driveway when we put in the fence, none of that is changing either.
The area a potential patio might extend to is staying grass for now, so there wasn’t a concern about installing permanent plantings when they might turn out to be in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plants&quot;&gt;Plants…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plant selection was probably the most time-consuming (and most fun) part of the process.
I didn’t have much plant knowledge coming into this, so I really dove headfirst into the subject.
Starting with themed areas helped a lot, as the different sections of the yard naturally lent themselves to different kinds of plants.
The food area got vegetables and other edibles, the wildlife area got native plants, and the back of the lot got a permaculture food forest palette.
Focusing on these areas one at a time gave me a way to direct my research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the resources I found most useful in this were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tobyhemenway.com/book/gaias-garden/&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Gaia's Garden&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Offers some good starter lists of permaculture favorites, and in-depth profiles of a few specific plants the detail how they might be best put to use.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chelseagreen.com/product/edible-forest-gardens-volume-ii/&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Edible Forest Gardens, Volume Two&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;The back of the book is a huge set of appendices with fabulous plant lists for a permaculture focus. Would that every resource was this thorough.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/perennial-vegetables-from-artichoke-to-zuiki-taro-a-gardeners-guide-to-over-100-delicious-easy-to-grow-edibles/oclc/636660344?loc=&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Perennial Vegetables&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;A guide to edible perennial plants, a subject I was specifically interested in. Not a perfect book but a good companion piece to the others.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/birdscaping-in-the-midwest-a-guide-to-gardening-with-native-plants-to-attract-birds/oclc/80180291?loc=&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Birdscaping in the Midwest&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;A thorough and informative guide to attracting all sorts of birds. Excellent plant lists, second only to &lt;cite&gt;Edible Forest Gardens&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/attracting-butterflies-hummingbirds-to-your-backyard-watch-your-garden-come-alive-with-beauty-on-the-wing/oclc/893647163?loc=&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Attracting Butterflies &amp;amp; Hummingbirds to Your Backyard&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Just like it says, a guide to creating plants and habitat for hummingbirds and butterflies. These were two types of wildlife I was specifically interested in, so it was a great fit.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Seed catalogs&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Some of the catalogs seed companies put out offer a lot of good information on the plants they sell. Fedco has very good paper catalogs for both trees and vegetables. [Prairie Moon](https://www.prairiemoon.com/)'s online and paper catalogs are excellent reference sources for native plants in our region.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Plant lists&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;There are lots of sample plant lists for native plants floating around. I collected a variety including some from Blue Thumb, Xerces, and UMN's Bee Lab. If I were starting today my first stop would be the resources in the [Lawns to Legumes program guide](https://bwsr.state.mn.us/sites/default/files/2020-06/Planting%20for%20Pollinators_updated_2020.pdf). The plant lists and sample plans are high quality and easy to use.&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://plants.usda.gov&quot;&gt;USDA Plants Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;This tool isn't the easiest to use, but it contains a ton of information. I used it to check if a plant was considered native to the state, to find scientific names for plants, and to help untangle the taxonomy of plants with confusing classifications (lookin' at you, &quot;serviceberry&quot;). Some plants also have more detailed fact sheets or plant guides, which can offer detailed information on growing characteristics (though these are often aimed towards agriculture or forestry). They also have a ton of searchable plant characteristics that I feel like I have only scratched the surface of. For example, I figured out how to search for MN natives with &quot;medium&quot; or &quot;high&quot; nitrogen fixing capabilities and got several useful plant suggestions from that.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/master-list-1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/master-list-480.png 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/master-list-800.png 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/master-list-1200.png 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/master-list.png 3086w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        A glimpse into my master plant list.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plant research mania hit a peak with the creation of the “master list” I used to track potential plants and their attributes.
Many of the fields were cribbed from the extensive and detailed charts in &lt;cite&gt;Edible Forest Gardens, Volume Two&lt;/cite&gt;.
Any plant I came across in research that sounded interesting was added to the list, and if it entered serious consideration, I’d fill out as many of the fields as I could find information for.
This gave me a quick reference for design characteristics like size, sun, and moisture preferences.
It also helped me track which of the traits I cared most about were met by each plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When choosing plants, the primary criteria for me is: what functions does this plant serve?
Ideally, everything we grow should serve multiple purposes (in the permaculture world, this is called “stacking functions”).
For example, a large serviceberry shrub on the north side of our lot can provide: attractive spring flowers and beautiful fall foliage; a partial screen from the sidewalk; early season food for pollinators; tasty berries for birds and humans; perching spots and cover for birds; habitat for a variety of insects; a deep root system that sequesters carbon, improves the soil, and allows for water penetration; and leaves that filter dust and pollutants.
While it might sound very complicated to look at plants in this multi-faceted way, I felt that it actually made the job easier by narrowing my scope to selections of plants that have a lot to offer.
Notably, I have been able to almost entirely ignore the vast world of decorative nursery perennials, because those plants are often bred solely for appearance and in my garden a single function is not enough to warrant consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of functions dovetailed perfectly with the considerations I had &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-plan-a-garden-part-one.html&quot;&gt;previously mapped out&lt;/a&gt; with zones and sectors, as finer-grained details within the general themes.
For example, when picking plants for the northeast corner, the general theme dictated that they contribute to a woodland feel and four-season beauty.
From sectors, I knew that they should be attractive from the public sidewalk as well as our picture window, that they should be able to withstand the strong winds that enter at that corner, and that they should provide a windbreak to protect the rest of the yard.
From zones, I knew that they should be relatively self-sufficient because I wouldn’t be dragging a hose up there all that often to water them, and I wouldn’t be passing through every day to deal with weeds or other maintenance.
Red-twig dogwood meets all of those criteria perfectly, plus is a native plant with excellent wildlife value, so it got the nod in that area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/master-list-sources-1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/master-list-sources-480.png 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/master-list-sources-800.png 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/master-list-sources-1200.png 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/master-list-sources.png 3080w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The master list eventually generated several offshoots, like this plant sourcing list.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like now would be a good time to point out that you certainly do not need to go this deep to do a successful garden design.
This sort of highly detailed data-heavy process suits my personality, and besides, I was very excited about the whole project.
But many people are perfectly successful using a much less rigorous process, so don’t be intimidated by my spreadsheet version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://crazywalls.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;the crazy wall&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-where-to-put-them&quot;&gt;…and where to put them&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When deciding on the exact placement of plants, there a number of other questions to consider besides meeting the desired functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How big will the plant be at maturity?
What is its habit (i.e. shape) and will that be a good fit for where it is?
How much sun does it like and will it receive the right amount (both right now, and once the plantings are fully established)?
Will it create the right amount of sun at maturity for surrounding plants?
What sort of root system does it have and will that coexist with other plants nearby?
Does it spread or stay in one place, and is that what you want it to do?
Will it receive the right amount of moisture?
Is the plant hardy in your zone, or if it’s borderline, will it receive extra protection?
Will the plant be happy with the soil pH?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For spacing, I largely adhered to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://permies.com/t/153438/Dense-Wide-Spacing-Food-Forests#1214206&quot;&gt;“crowns touching” rule&lt;/a&gt;.
In hindsight now that we’ve had a few years of growth, I think I made the right decision on tree spacing but I could have planted many of the shrubs and forbs more densely.
As &lt;a href=&quot;https://permies.com/t/153438/Dense-Wide-Spacing-Food-Forests#1203185&quot;&gt;this commenter&lt;/a&gt; notes, “most people put their trees too close together, but then don’t plant enough support species”.
I’ve been slowly filling in my original plantings with additional understory plants as I realize there’s space for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing the designs was a highly iterative process.
I worked primarily with the trees and shrubs in most sections, as those are the most permanent and most structural plants.
For each section, I put together a short list of possible plants using the resources listed above, then sketched out different placements and combinations to see what worked well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rain garden was one of the most complicated areas, reflected in the number of different concepts I considered for it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;fade&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-1-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of a potential rain garden layout&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-1-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-1-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-1-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/rain-garden-sketch-1.jpg 1702w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-2-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of a potential rain garden layout&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-2-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-2-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-2-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/rain-garden-sketch-2.jpg 1878w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-3-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of a potential rain garden layout&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-3-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-3-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-3-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/rain-garden-sketch-3.jpg 1878w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-4-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of a potential rain garden layout&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-4-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-4-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-4-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/rain-garden-sketch-4.jpg 1878w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-5-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of a potential rain garden layout&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-5-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-5-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-sketch-5-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/rain-garden-sketch-5.jpg 1878w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had a base map, I could use tracing paper to quickly create copies of a map to sketch different ideas on.
For the back of the lot, which had a lot of flexibility, I wanted to quickly visualize many different layouts and combinations of different plant sizes.
I cut out a bunch of circles of different sizes representing standard, semi-dwarf, and dwarf fruit trees, as well as small and large shrubs.
I could push these around on the map as I thought through how to best make use of that space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;fade&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/back-nine-paper-sketch-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Map of the back area of the lot with loose circles of paper laid out&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/back-nine-paper-sketch-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/back-nine-paper-sketch-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/back-nine-paper-sketch-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/back-nine-paper-sketch.jpg 1948w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/back-nine-sketch-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of the back area of the lot&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/back-nine-sketch-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/back-nine-sketch-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/back-nine-sketch-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/back-nine-sketch.jpg 1926w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the side of the house, I was also interested in the vertical dimension of the planting, as we wanted to partially screen our windows but not create an impenetrable wall.
Once I had a layout that looked good from the “top-down” perspective, I drew a scaled side view to help me imagine what it would look like from the sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-profile-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A sketch of the rain garden layout from the side&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-profile-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-profile-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-profile-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/rain-garden-profile.jpg 2400w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to making sure the plans looked good on paper, I vetted them on the ground itself to make sure they felt good there as well.
I used stakes to mark the center of major elements and spray paint to mark the outlines of trees, bushes, or other structural elements.
This helped me visualize the final result and gave me a chance to walk out potential borders and pathways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;slide&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/paint-tree-layout-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/paint-tree-layout-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/paint-tree-layout-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/paint-tree-layout-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/paint-tree-layout.jpg 1800w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Paint and stakes to mark the mature size of a tree canopy
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/paint-rain-garden-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/paint-rain-garden-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/paint-rain-garden-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/paint-rain-garden-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/paint-rain-garden.jpg 1800w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Paint for the outline of the rain garden depression, stakes for trees and shrubs
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/snow-tree-layout-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/snow-tree-layout-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/snow-tree-layout-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/snow-tree-layout-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/snow-tree-layout.jpg 1800w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        As an alternative, just stomp circles in the snow to mark tree locations!
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the “bones” of the landscape decided, I filled in the designs with the “forbs” (non-woody plants) I wanted.
This process was similar to the trees and shrubs, though often easier because there is a lot more flexibility in placement of smaller plants.
What plants went into the design depended on what plants I could source, so this part involved iterations of looking at plant lists from local vendors, adjusting the design, rechecking the plant lists, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-draft-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-draft-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-draft-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/rain-garden-draft-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/rain-garden-draft.jpg 1820w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        A not-quite-final version of the rain garden design, with forbs filled in.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some areas didn’t get detailed schematics of every plant ahead of time, but rather a rough plan of plant selections and quantities that I’d finalize at planting time.
And of course the iterative design process continued after planting, as I would realize I had more room to fill, or would need to replace a plant that wasn’t doing well, or would find a new exciting plant and need to figure out where to fit it in.
I consider the maps living documents, and try to keep them updated as things change (though my track record on that has been spotty).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time--materials&quot;&gt;Time &amp;amp; Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have any idea how much time went into planning, as it was conducted in bits and pieces over many months.
I will say, though, that I spent a very substantial amount of time on it—many tens of hours.
Some of that was because I was learning a ton about plants and ecosystems and wildlife and landscape management as I went.
Some of it was because I was very enthusiastic and went into way more depth than was strictly necessary.
Still, planning a design of this magnitude is a definite commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary cost &quot;&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal-heading&quot;&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Books &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tobyhemenway.com/book/gaias-garden/&quot;&gt;Gaia’s Garden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$30 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chelseagreen.com/product/edible-forest-gardens-volume-ii/&quot;&gt;Edible Forest Gardens, Volume Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$62 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/perennial-vegetables-from-artichoke-to-zuiki-taro-a-gardeners-guide-to-over-100-delicious-easy-to-grow-edibles/oclc/636660344?loc=&quot;&gt;Perennial Vegetables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$15 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/birdscaping-in-the-midwest-a-guide-to-gardening-with-native-plants-to-attract-birds/oclc/80180291?loc=&quot;&gt;Birdscaping in the Midwest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;library &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/attracting-butterflies-hummingbirds-to-your-backyard-watch-your-garden-come-alive-with-beauty-on-the-wing/oclc/893647163?loc=&quot;&gt;Attracting Butterflies &amp;amp; Hummingbirds to Your Backyard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;library &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$107 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal-heading&quot;&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Drafting supplies &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;4x4 graph paper
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;existing &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001KZH2DC/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o02_s01?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;10x10 graph paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$6 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004GXBXSK/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o02_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Tracing paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$6 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000KIDVJE/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o06_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Circle drawing template&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$7 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000HEOI0W/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o06_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Triangular scale ruler&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$6 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000JQSV7E/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o00_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Clutch pencil&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$7 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005M306U4/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o00_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Compass&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$9 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.homedepot.com/p/Rust-Oleum-Professional-15-oz-Fluorescent-Red-Orange-2X-Distance-Inverted-Marking-Spray-Paint-266590/203302842&quot;&gt;Inverted marking paint&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$6 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$47 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;total&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$154 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Garden" /><category term="How to" /><summary type="html">My journey thus far in landscape design had arrived at a high-level plan for the yard that split it into segments with themes driving the design.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to plan a garden, part one: the vision</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/how-to-plan-a-garden-part-one.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to plan a garden, part one: the vision" /><published>2021-02-04T21:10:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T21:10:00-06:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/how-to-plan-a-garden-part-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/how-to-plan-a-garden-part-one.html">&lt;p&gt;With our new house, I was very excited to start planning our garden and landscaping, but to be honest also very intimidated.
I had done a bit of gardening at our rentals over the years, but always at a fairly small scale.
I knew I wanted to go much bigger with my ambitions, but I didn’t have any experience in landscape design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our yard is quite big for the inner city.
It’s a full double lot (just under a quarter acre) and our house has a fairly small footprint, so there’s plenty of space left over.
Other than a couple huge trees, the yard was entirely turfgrass when we moved in, and I knew I wanted to kill most of that.
This meant that I had a blank slate to work with, and while great in a lot of ways, that also meant that I didn’t have anything to guide my decisions or limit my options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that I needed help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;slide&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/start1-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the yard when we bought the house&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/start1-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/start1-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/start1-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/start1.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The future is wide open.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/start2-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the yard when we bought the house&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/start2-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/start2-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/start2-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/start2.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        So. Much. Grass.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have gone with a traditional landscape design firm, but I hate to imagine how much they would have charged me for a set of fancy full-color plans.
Besides, this wouldn’t have been a good fit for how I wanted to manage the garden.
I wanted to handle most of the installation and maintenance myself, and I knew the design would need to change over time.
This meant I needed a strong understanding of the rationale behind the design and how all the pieces fit together—not something I was likely to get out of having a complete set of plans dropped in my lap.
I also wanted a garden that was uniquely tailored to our needs, not just the same ten plants that the landscaper uses in every yard they design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paid a garden consultant to do a site visit and draw up an informal set of layouts.
While I didn’t end up using most of her designs, the process did get me started thinking about how to determine how to use a space, and it gave me a sense of the possibilities available to us.
I could start to see the shape of the thing I needed to do, I just needed a lot more practical information to actually be able to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;observe-and-interact&quot;&gt;Observe and Interact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best decisions I made in the planning process was forced upon me.
We finished a rocky closing process for our house at the end of April, and the timesuck of buying a house, moving, and being first-time homeowners meant that I had very little time to plan or prepare as planting season rolled around in May.
This necessarily limited how much I could expect to achieve in the first year, so I planted &lt;a href=&quot;/the-first-year-garden.html&quot;&gt;a modest vegetable garden&lt;/a&gt; and accepted that my bigger ambitions would need to wait a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was good, because major site planning decisions really should not be made until one has been able to observe conditions throughout a growing season.
I probably wouldn’t have followed this advice well if I had a few more months of lead time before spring, but I’m glad I didn’t have that choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending the first year observing allowed me to see how the site changed over time: what kind of runoff came from the house during rainstorms, where water pooled during wet periods, which areas got the most and least sun, where the grass grew well and where it didn’t, and so on.
It gave me time to take detailed measurements, draw maps, and conduct soil tests.
And it gave me time to learn a lot more, to roll ideas around in my head, to sketch out possibilities while looking at the site, and to get outside and pace out distances on the ground when I needed to see it in situ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-educated&quot;&gt;Getting educated&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I figured out in the process of reading about gardening stuff was that the permaculture philosophy greatly appealed to me.
What is permaculture?
There are many answers to that question, few of them short, but I like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.permaculturenews.org/what-is-permaculture/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; pretty well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Permaculture (the word, coined by Bill Mollison, is a portmanteau of permanent agriculture and permanent culture) is the conscious design and maintenance of agriculturally productive ecosystems which have the diversity, stability, and resilience of natural ecosystems… [It] is a system of assembling conceptual, material, and strategic components in a pattern which functions to benefit life in all its forms. The philosophy behind permaculture is one of working with, rather than against, nature; of protracted and thoughtful observation rather than protracted and thoughtless action; of looking at systems in all their functions, rather than asking only one yield of them; and allowing systems to demonstrate their own evolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a certain set of gardening practices (food forests, hugelkultur, comfrey) that have become associated with permaculture, some of which I do find appealing, but for me those were not as much of a draw as the whole-design nature of the idea.
Many other garden ideologies like organic gardening or square foot gardening tend to be centered around one specific concept plus a loose constellation of practices compatible with the core idea.
While many of them have useful advice to offer, I don’t find them compelling as an organizing principle for everything.
Permaculture, in being primarily a design philosophy, credibly promises guidance on the entirety of the system—not only how one manages a garden, but how a garden can fit into your life and the surrounding world.
It provides not only tools for thinking about design, but tools for thinking about the act of designing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My entry point for permaculture was Toby Hemenway’s &lt;i&gt;Gaia’s Garden&lt;/i&gt;.
It’s a lovely book that provides a very accessible overview of the concepts that drive permaculture design.
It’s not the final word on the subject, but it was a great place to learn the concepts and terminology, and to gather ideas about how I could apply these concepts in my own space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permaculture also gave me a descriptive term for exploring and discovering useful information.
Because it is aligned with many of the things I wanted out of the garden (beyond-organic, low-input, ecological), I could peruse permaculture sources as a starting point and learn about ideas and techniques that were likely to appeal to me.
It would be fair to point out that some permaculturists are pretty wacky and not all of their ideas are good.
I’m pretty skilled at sifting through information of varying quality, so this was not a big deal for me, but a more credulous person could be led astray by bad advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other major breakthrough in my planning education was probably the most valuable book purchase I’ve ever made: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chelseagreen.com/product/edible-forest-gardens-volume-ii/&quot;&gt;Edible Forest Gardens, Volume Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/book-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover of Edible Forest Gardens, Volume Two&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/book-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/book-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/book-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/book.jpg 1241w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Side note: there is a Volume One, which provides a conceptual background on permaculture and temperate climate forest gardens in particular.
It’s a perfectly nice book, but not essential if you’ve picked up the gist from other sources.
All the meat is in Volume Two, which focuses on practical applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Edible Forest Gardens, Volume Two&lt;/cite&gt; is a stellar permacultural resource, with extensive plant lists and tables.
But it’s also an excellent guide to the design process in general.
It offers an extremely thorough design program that you can follow to the letter or simply pluck out the parts that appeal to you, and it covers the whole spectrum from very broad exercises like defining the vision for your site, to very specific advice like the best way to plant a tree.
I referred to this book a ton throughout every step of my process.
It was particularly valuable early on, as I was struggling to figure out where to begin.
The design exercises gave me tools to move from ideas to action.
Let’s take a look at some of the interesting ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-begin&quot;&gt;Let’s begin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early part of the planning process was turning the dreams I had floating around in my head into concrete goals, large and small:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A large garden plot dedicated to food production&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fruit trees and berry bushes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food and habitat for pollinators, birds, and other wildlife&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As much of a fully-functioning natural ecosystem as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Features to draw charismatic wildlife such as hummingbirds and butterflies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beauty in all four seasons, both for our enjoyment and for passersby&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Areas for relaxing outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexible space for gatherings, activities, dog and child playtime, etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low maintenance burden&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A rain garden, probably&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lilac bushes (they’re my favorite flower)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had some site-specific constraints and issues to address.
Most of these were revealed during the observation period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The thin strip between the garage and alley was full of weeds and in bad condition, being an especially tough site.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Much of the lawn was lumpy and uneven.
Some areas had pretty good grass, but others were very weedy and/or patchy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since the yard is level with the public sidewalk, it feels very weird if there isn’t something to delineate the border.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The back of the lot, near the alley, was neglected and in terrible condition.
The soil was so compacted that nothing would grow there until it was improved.
Drainage was also very poor and it would remain very wet for a long time after rains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These lists provided a reference point I could return to at any time during the later stages of planning.
When considering a potential design, it’s often hard to decide “is this a good plan?”
It can be much easier to answer when reframed as “does this plan meet the criteria I laid out as important to me?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zones&quot;&gt;Zones&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One common permaculture planning tool is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permaculture#Zones&quot;&gt;“zones”&lt;/a&gt; (not to be confused with plant hardiness zones, which are a different thing entirely).
Zones are a framework for thinking about how location affects the manner and frequency of our interactions with a space, and planning our land use to be compatible with these factors.
Things that we use often, or that require frequent attention, should be located in areas that are easy to access and that we frequently visit.
Areas that are further from the house or harder to access will be visited less often, and are harder to supply with resources like water or compost.
We should use these areas for things that require fewer inputs and can take care of themselves without frequent weeding or other maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The canonical 5-zone framework is oriented towards larger tracts of land, like rural homesteads, and so many of the specifics are not as relevant to urban areas.
A city lot is unlikely to have zones 3 through 5 (farming, forage, and wilderness) located within its boundaries.
However, the general concepts are still a useful tool for planning an urban space.
Our yard very much has areas that are easier or harder to access, and visited more or less frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/zones-1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of our lot with zones marked out&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/zones-480.png 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/zones-800.png 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/zones-1200.png 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/zones.png 1800w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Our lot mapped with micro-scale zone designations.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The back of the lot, for example, is far enough from the house that most hoses don’t reach.
This means it’s a nuisance to water it, and therefore it will not be watered very often.
We also don’t pass through that area on the way to or from anywhere else, and we don’t spend time in that area to relax or work.
When planning what to do with it, I looked specifically for things that were resilient and largely self-sufficient.
While that area was a potential site for the vegetable garden in terms of size and sun, I knew relatively high-maintenance vegetables were something that should go in a closer zone if possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strip between the alley and garage is even further out, zone-wise.
Not only is it far from the house, it’s completely out of sight from almost everywhere in the house and yard.
Out of sight, out of mind!
Therefore, my top criteria for any use of that site was that it had to succeed under severe neglect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest zone in our lot is probably the area right outside the back door.
This is very close to the kitchen, and we pass through multiple times per day on the way to the garage, driveway, or out for walks.
This would be an ideal site for herbs and other plants that need frequent access or attention, but unfortunately this area is also heavily shaded by the white pines, so most options would not do well there.
I would compromise on these things and put them in a location that wasn’t quite as frequently visited but provided much better growing conditions.
Zones aren’t the final word, but rather a useful tool to be used as part of a toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sectors&quot;&gt;Sectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another planning tool described in &lt;em&gt;Edible Forest Gardens&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.oregonstate.education/permaculture/chapter/sectors/&quot;&gt;“sectors”&lt;/a&gt; and “flows”.
While these are commonly described in terms of directional forces, I think the real power of the technique lies in giving shape and location to various invisible aspects of a site.
When we create maps, they tend to identify tangible things: here’s the dimensions of the house, here’s the path, here’s some trees, here’s a hill.
But where does the sun shine in winter?
Which views are desirable or undesirable?
What enters the site from neighboring areas—wildlife, odors, light, seeds, pollution?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/sectors-1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of our lot with sectors marked out&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/sectors-480.png 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/sectors-800.png 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/sectors-1200.png 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/sectors.png 1800w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        A sector-ish analysis applied to our lot.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking in terms of sectors helped me distill a bunch of observations about our site into a concise and useful format that could be used alongside other maps to inform my decisions.
Some key takeaways for us were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Several windows on the first floor of the house look out onto sections of the yard, and we would like those to be nice views of some sort.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our north-facing windows are close to the street, and with only empty space between the house and the sidewalk, it made our dining room feel exposed to people walking past.
It would be nice to have something to partially screen the view.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The wind can really rip across parts of the lot.
The worst seems to be north winds traveling across the front yard.
These are not only unpleasant, but prove destructive at times, knocking over crops and causing other minor damage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The alley is not a charming view and would do well to be screened. The garage is also not a great view.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We only have one immediate next-door neighbor, who is quiet and easy to get along with.
We don’t need major screening in that direction, though something to slow down the entry of weed seeds might be nice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The house gets limited sun in the winter, so we should not do anything to further limit that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Due to the corner lot, we have a lot of interface with the public sidewalks and roads.
This gives our yard a lot of potential to be appreciated from the outside as well as from the inside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sun-surveys&quot;&gt;Sun surveys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll probably do a more in-depth post on sun surveys at some point.
Since sunlight is one of the most important factors to plants’ success, it’s very valuable to know how much sun an area receives when you are deciding what to plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My early sun surveying was done informally by simply paying attention and mentally noting where sun and shade fell throughout the 2017 growing season.
Later, I would do the process more formally by systematically photographing the yard over the course of the day to document the sun and shade.
This latter method took more work and planning, but offers much more exact detail, which is useful in more precise planning.
The informal method was good enough for my initial needs of delineating the yard into general areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/sun-1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of our lot with sun exposure marked&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/sun-480.png 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/sun-800.png 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/sun-1200.png 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/sun.png 1563w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        A very rough estimate of sun and shade on our lot. I didn't use this during planning, it's just for your edification.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun data was vital to deciding where to place the vegetable garden.
In order to get the best production out of many types of vegetables, I needed to make sure it was located in “full sun” (6+ hours of sun per day).
I would also use sun information heavily when planning other plantings, like the rain garden.
The area selected for that has a mixture of different sun types, so when designing I selected a variety of different natives and made sure to locate each plant somewhere with conditions that suited it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sun is important to humans as well as plants.
I considered sun conditions carefully when selecting the areas that would be maintained for leisure.
Katherine especially likes to bask in the hot sun like a lizard, so I made sure to accommodate her needs with several spots for relaxing that receive sun at different times of the day.
Since it’s sometimes more comfortable to be in the shade, I was also careful to leave several spots that allow for that.
Thanks to the placement of the house and some large trees, these spots change roles over the course of the day, so an area that was sunny in the morning will be shaded by afternoon, while another area that was shaded in the morning is now in sun.
This gives us a lot of flexibility and encourages us to be outside as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;heres-the-plan&quot;&gt;Here’s the plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going through these exercises, in combination with a lot of time to simply look at our yard and think about it, helped me through my decision paralysis.
With all this information distilled into discrete lists of attributes, I could start piecing combinations together like a logic puzzle.
Some areas had specific problems that needed solving, and so should host something that solved that problem.
Some of the features I wanted to add had specific placement needs, and so those would get first priority on suitable sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that given the size of our yard and the wide variety of features I wanted, the easiest way to develop a sensible plan would be to break the yard up into several broad areas, each with their own theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/general-plan-1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of our lot with themed areas marked&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/general-plan-480.png 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/general-plan-800.png 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/resized/general-plan-1200.png 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/how-to-plan-a-garden/general-plan.png 1456w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The southwest corner got a “food production” theme and would host the vegetable garden.
Sub-themes for this area were “beneficial insects”, because insects are useful to food plots for pollination and pest control, and “visually interesting”, because it is situated at the front of the lot and should be pleasant for us to look at from the porch and passersby to look at from the sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The north side of the house got a “wildlife” theme. There is a fair amount of space there, but we were never likely to spend much time there ourselves, so it made sense to set it aside for the benefit of insects and birds.
I knew this theme would lend itself well to low-maintenance plantings, which was a definite plus for this area (despite being close to the house, it’s not particularly close to either door, and it’s a bit hard to reach with a hose).
Other considerations for this area were that we wanted beautiful views out of our windows, and we wanted some tall plantings along the sidewalk to partially screen the house.
Both of these would fit well with wildlife plantings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;East of the house got a “people” theme.
This is where we spend the most time hanging out in the yard, and where we host gatherings, play games, etc.
This was the area most likely to remain partially turfgrass, though I planned to add some borders to provide beauty and partial screening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The northeast corner got a “wild” theme.
This area was furthest from the house and any sidewalk and thus needed things that could mostly fend for themselves.
Because of its position, it could afford to be a bit unruly without inconveniencing anyone.
It also had some serious soil quality problems that made it unsuitable for more delicate plants, lacking a major intervention.
Since this space wasn’t in high demand for anything else, I knew it would be an excellent place for some of the bigger features I wanted to add, like fruit trees.
The extended timeline of establishing a “food forest” would work well here.
Trees would eventually fill in most of the space, but while they were small I could grow other things around them to hold off the weeds and improve the soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;West of the house got a “beauty” theme.
In particular, I wanted some part of the yard to have excellent winter interest, and with this area bordering the sidewalk and visible from our front picture window, it seemed like a good place.
Had I been working with a smaller yard, I could have folded the “beauty” theme into the other themes with some clever plant placement, but because I had plenty of space to work with, I felt I was able to give it a dedicated space.
As I got into more detail on what exactly I would plant, this theme morphed into “woodland beauty”.
This blended well with the bordering “wildlife” area, extending the wildlife zone further and giving the whole side yard a naturalistic landscaping feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The south side of the house just had a “flex” theme, which meant I wasn’t sure what we’d do with it and would keep our options open for now.
The &lt;a href=&quot;/the-first-year-garden.html&quot;&gt;first-year garden&lt;/a&gt; was there, so the conversion of that into prairie would augment the pollinator needs of the neighboring food production area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The southeast corner got a loose “dog &amp;amp; birds” theme, which was more a descriptive label based on its current use.
I didn’t have a strong vision for how to use that area and figuring it out was not a high priority.
This part of the yard is dominated by the two giant white pines, so they drove a lot of the use.
The grass wasn’t doing well in their heavy shade, so I’d get rid of that and plant something more appropriate.
We’d have some wood chips and hopefully get the dog to do most of her bathroom business over there.
The trees already attracted a lot of bird activity, so maybe we’d add some feeders or birdhouses to augment that.
This is also the best shade from hot midday sun, so we’d leave some area for us to use on days where we needed some relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;were-just-getting-started&quot;&gt;We’re just getting started&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This macro-level plan seems so straightforward in hindsight, but reaching this point felt like the hardest part of the process.
With my themed areas as the guiding document, the rest of the design seemed to flow naturally out of it.
That’s not to say I didn’t have a ton of work still ahead of me, though.
I had a lot of research and designing left to do, which we’ll cover in part two.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Garden" /><category term="How to" /><summary type="html">With our new house, I was very excited to start planning our garden and landscaping, but to be honest also very intimidated. I had done a bit of gardening at our rentals over the years, but always at a fairly small scale. I knew I wanted to go much bigger with my ambitions, but I didn’t have any experience in landscape design.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Mud Head</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/the-mud-head.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mud Head" /><published>2021-01-21T23:29:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T23:29:00-06:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/the-mud-head</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/the-mud-head.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-bolt-of-inspiration&quot;&gt;A bolt of inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/basement-egress.html&quot;&gt;basement egress window installation&lt;/a&gt; left us with a giant pile of dirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/dirt-pile-in-progress-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of a very large pile of dirt&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/dirt-pile-in-progress-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/dirt-pile-in-progress-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/dirt-pile-in-progress-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/dirt-pile-in-progress.jpg 1574w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowly redistributed this to other places around the yard as I added garden beds, but some of the the subsoil they had dug up was heavy clay.
Hard to work within garden beds, not great for plants, and if left on the surface, prone to drying into useless rock-hard chunks.
I started separating out this clay soil and setting it aside as I moved all the other stuff, so as I reached the end of the pile I was left with probably about 20 gallons of clay soil with no real purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/clay-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of a pile of heavy clay soil&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/clay-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/clay-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/clay-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/clay.jpg 1404w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I contemplated what to do with all this clay, one particular idea floated to the top and stayed there.
In season 2 of the delightful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b07237wd&quot;&gt;Big Dreams, Small Spaces&lt;/a&gt;, Monty Don helps the mildly eccentric Frankie renovate her country cottage garden.
Frankie pursues her garden dream of a mud head against Monty’s direct advice.
It’s a completely mad idea and she absolutely nails it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BCQNRZ2gOiy/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;13&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:16px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BCQNRZ2gOiy/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 19% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;&quot;&gt;&lt;svg width=&quot;50px&quot; height=&quot;50px&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 60 60&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; xmlns=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; xmlns:xlink=&quot;https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot;&gt;&lt;g stroke=&quot;none&quot; stroke-width=&quot;1&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot;&gt;&lt;g transform=&quot;translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)&quot; fill=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;g&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding-top: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;&quot;&gt; View this post on Instagram&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 12.5% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: auto;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BCQNRZ2gOiy/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Do you watch Monty Dons gardening programme last night? The &amp;#39;mud head&amp;#39; was brilliant - ears supplied by us! www.mhwoodland.co.uk #gardening #montydon #woodlandtheme #rustic #wood #mudhead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A post shared by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/mhwoodland/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; MH Woodland&lt;/a&gt; (@mhwoodland) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2016-02-26T14:42:51+00:00&quot;&gt;Feb 26, 2016 at 6:42am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned the mud head to Katherine and she, much like Monty, expressed extreme skepticism about the idea.
Well guess what?
Frankie and I both know that sometimes you just gotta believe in yourself and your weird mud head, and that anyways you can just wait until the doubters aren’t around and build it then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to do some research and found a dearth of information on mud head construction methods.
Apparently there are not a lot of people in the world building mud heads.
I can’t imagine why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems likely that mud sculpture is an ancient art, but any information about traditional methods must be buried in anthropological journals or something.
There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.heligan.com/explore/estate/woodland&quot;&gt;a couple&lt;/a&gt; famous mud sculptures that get some press, but most of these are large and seem to incorporate something like a mesh structure to be fitted with moss plugs.
My mud head was going to be much smaller and less sophisticated, plus situated in full sun without regular watering.
This meant moss was likely out as a covering and I was on my own design-wise.
I decided not to overthink it and que será, será.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-go&quot;&gt;Let’s go&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction was pretty simple.
The dirt had been under a tarp and was at a good level of moistness.
I hauled it to the spot in a five-gallon bucket, one load at a time.
First I built a base platform and “watered it in”, trying to get rid of air pockets for a solid, stable foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/base-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Base of the mud sculpture&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/base-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/base-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/base-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/base.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once most of it was there, I shaped it into a rough head and started molding the densest clumps of clay into the features.
I shaped it on a gentle slant and tried to design the face so that there were no wells where water would collect.
Once the features were roughed in, it was just a matter of refining the shape and prominence of the features and adding details until it looked the way I wanted (suitably dramatic).
I gotta say, it turned out better than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;slide&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/finished-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finished mud sculpture&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/finished-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/finished-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/finished-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/finished.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/finished-large-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finished mud sculpture&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/finished-large-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/finished-large-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/finished-large.jpg 1200w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the head finished, I smoothed the surface as much as I could and left it to bake in the hot sun, hoping that would harden up the outer shell.
I had intentionally chosen a period of time in midsummer with a dry, sunny forecast to tip the odds in my favor.
Katherine told me it was weird and then didn’t bring it up again.
Her loss if she’s not going to appreciate my work of art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;long-term-performance&quot;&gt;Long-term performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial plan worked well and the head firmed up nicely.
I also covered it with a tarp during rain for the first few weeks, hoping if I gave it more time it would become more resilient to weathering.
It developed a few cracks as it dried, which I tried to patch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/cracks-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cracks developing on the mud head&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/cracks-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/cracks-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/resized/cracks-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-mud-head/cracks.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, as I had suspected, unfired clay soil just doesn’t have the strength to hold up to Midwest weather.
The head did okay for a while after I exposed it to the elements, but within months it was showing definite signs of degrading.
The nose fell off at some point (shoutout to Egypt’s sphinx, ze gets it).
By the end of the summer, the head had degraded to the point of not being recognizable.
I left it where it was, to become a mound of soil slowly melding back into the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect the secret to making a mud head maintain its integrity would be to cover it in living plant matter.
Roots would stabilize the soil structure and leaves would shield it from battering rain.
Moss is a likely candidate but didn’t seem likely to do well in my site.
The most promising idea I came up with was Elfin Thyme, a cultivar of thyme that is especially low growing with small leaves.
If Elfin Thyme could establish successfully, it ought to spread to eventually form a thick, low mat of vegetation hugging the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspected that given the small size of my mud head (about 1.5 feet in each dimension), the features would likely be drowned out by a cover of vegetation.
It would also have taken a fair amount of effort, and I wasn’t quite invested enough in this idea to commit to that.
Thus, my decision to let this be an ephemeral masterpiece, soon to exist only in memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were to set a goal in the future of establishing a permanent mud head, I think I’d aim to make it substantially larger (maybe 5 feet in each dimension), reinforce it with mesh or straw cob, and plant it immediately with plugs of thyme.
Katherine better watch her back.
You never know when I’ll get a burst of motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time--materials&quot;&gt;Time &amp;amp; Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary time&quot;&gt;&lt;caption class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Time &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Sculpting
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;2 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Maintenance
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;0.5 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;total&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;2.5 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary cost&quot;&gt;&lt;caption class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Materials &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Clay soil
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;free &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Garden" /><summary type="html">A bolt of inspiration</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The first-year garden</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/the-first-year-garden.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The first-year garden" /><published>2021-01-11T23:52:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-11T23:52:00-06:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/the-first-year-garden</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/the-first-year-garden.html">&lt;p&gt;I had maintained a small garden at both of the last two places we rented, so now that we had a place of our own I was excited to get a garden going.
However, we closed on the house at the end of April, and were consumed with moving and some of the more pressing move-in issues after that.
The timeline meant that I wasn’t going to have time to do almost any prep work before planting time rolled around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, this was a blessing in disguise for me.
It forced me to temper my ambitions for the first year, and that gave me a whole growing season to observe and learn about the condition of the land.
Thus, when I did start making more permanent decisions I did so well-informed.
In the moment, though, it meant I had to get creative about what I could scrap together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already present was a small corner near the porch that was absolutely packed with hostas, and one small raised bed, oddly nestled against a juniper.
Not much to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/rabbit-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A rabbit lying down in an empty raised bed&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/rabbit-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/rabbit-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/rabbit.jpg 1200w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        This rabbit prefers we leave the bed unused, thanks.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-circle-garden&quot;&gt;The circle garden&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was one more feature in the yard that could have been a problem but instead I saw as an opportunity.
The previous residents had kept an enormous above-ground pool in the side yard for quite a few years.
The pool was gone when we moved in, but in its place was a large circular patch of totally bare dirt.
It was a good size for a garden, and planting it with vegetables was going to be a lot more fun than letting the weeds plant it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a halfhearted job of double-digging the circle to loosen up the soil.
In the process I discovered that some sections of the space had about 8” of decent soil before hitting a layer of compacted rocks and rubble—this would be a recurring theme in the yard.
It quickly became clear that digging into this compacted layer and sifting out the rocks would take far too much time and effort.
This was a temporary site, not a permanent one, so it didn’t need to be perfect.
I dug down as far as the good soil and left the stuff below it alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was already past planting time, so as soon as it was ready I started putting things in the ground.
I had some seeds from previous years, and I bought some starts at the Friends Plant Sale and a couple neighborhood plant sales.
I also acquired a few plants from neighbors giving away extras, though one of those I would come to regret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planks salvaged from &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/06/20/the-garage.html&quot;&gt;the garage&lt;/a&gt; formed makeshift paths, and I got a bale of straw from a garden center for mulch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-july-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The garden in early July&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-july-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-july-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-july-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/circle-garden-july.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rabbits started snipping things the moment I planted.
Luckily I was cruising the free section on Nextdoor pretty heavily around this time and had acquired some chicken wire and t-posts, so that made a makeshift fence.
At some point I got some landscape staples and used those to hold down the bottom of the fence, and that arrangement provided sufficient protection throughout the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-bed&quot;&gt;Bonus bed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the circle garden, the small raised bed was available for use, so I planted it with tomatoes and a few flowers and other leftovers.
This bed didn’t have any critter protection, but thankfully the rabbits around here have never shown any interest in tomato plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/raised-bed-june-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The raised bed in late June&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/raised-bed-june-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/raised-bed-june-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/raised-bed-june.jpg 1147w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The juniper right next to the bed, however, got in the way of maintenance and harvesting.
I never figured out what the logic was in this placement.
The boards were also rotting and coming apart, so I didn’t expect this bed to exist beyond this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pretty-good-results&quot;&gt;Pretty good results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the limited amount of site preparation and the numerous imperfections in my process, I feel like I got as good of results as I could have hoped for.
There was remarkably little weed pressure–I think the pool must have been in place for so long that the weed seeds underneath it had rotted or lost viability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-peas-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Peas and marigolds in the circle garden&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-peas-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-peas-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-peas-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/circle-garden-peas.jpg 1336w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the vegetables grew well, considering the soil hadn’t been amended or improved in any way.
I did buy some liquid fertilizer that I applied to the tomatoes and flowers a couple times.
It’s from a local company that grinds up invasive carp into &lt;a href=&quot;https://twomikes.net/?page_id=37&quot;&gt;a nutrient-rich fish juice&lt;/a&gt;.
What a great use for an unwanted species!
As you might imagine, it smells a bit fishy when applied, but that smell is gone by the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got a nice crop of tomatoes, which is good because they are a top garden priority around here.
The greens were also good, with more arugula than I could harvest and a stellar performance from the “Amish Deer Tongue” lettuce, which has earned itself a permanent place in my planting lineup.
Beans and peas are always a good bet, and we had a nice mix of herbs too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;slide&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-midsummer-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The circle garden in late summer&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-midsummer-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-midsummer-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/circle-garden-midsummer-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/circle-garden-midsummer.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/raised-bed-midsummer-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The raised bed in late summer&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/raised-bed-midsummer-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/raised-bed-midsummer-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/raised-bed-midsummer-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/raised-bed-midsummer.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say there weren’t failures.
I planted quite a few herb and flower seeds that never germinated.
Many of these were from packets I’d been holding on to for years, so it’s likely a lot of the seeds were just too old.
I tried to grow a tomato plant from saved seed, but lacking any way to start it indoors, I just direct-seeded in mid-May and it barely reached maturity before the weather got too cold.
We also impulse-purchased some Prairie Smoke plants without any specific plan on what to do with them.
Well, those are fairly reticent native perennials that take several years to establish before flowering, so not a great choice for a garden-in-transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made one more error that seemed small at the time but would come back to haunt me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sunchoke-mistake&quot;&gt;The sunchoke mistake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunchokes, also known as Jerusalem Artichokes, are a perennial relative of the sunflower with tasty edible tubers.
They are also often described as an aggressive spreader, to be treated with care.
I took these warnings too lightly and paid for it.
When someone on Nextdoor offered free baby sunchokes dug from their yard, I biked over and grabbed a handful of starts, which I plopped in the middle of the circle garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistake #1: &lt;em&gt;Right&lt;/em&gt; in the middle of the garden.
My thinking at the time was that they were taller so they could be flanked by shorter plants without blocking views or sun.
In retrospect, what I actually did was provide them with a ton of open soil to colonize and no barriers to keep them contained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistake #2: I suspect these sunchokes were a wild type.
There are cultivars that produce bigger tubers and spread less vigorously, but these were probably the undomesticated variety.
I’ve since reined in my use of free plants from neighbors, in large part because of this sort of loss of control over the finer details of what gets planted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sunchokes grew okay through the season, though they “lodged” (i.e. fell over) after enduring some moderate winds.
The first disappointment came when I dug them at the end of the season and discovered that they had created almost no edible tubers.
Their root systems contained a few tubers too tiny to be practical and a ton of rhizomes (long-distance horizontal roots), and if that sounds like foreshadowing it’s because it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real bad news arrived the following spring (2018), when hundreds of volunteer sunchoke plants appeared all around the circle garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/sunchoke-volunteers-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Volunteer sunchokes all over the garden&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/sunchoke-volunteers-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/sunchoke-volunteers-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/sunchoke-volunteers-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/sunchoke-volunteers.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I've made a huge mistake.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only were there a ton clustered around where I had planted the sunchokes the previous year, but seedlings were also showing up as far as five feet away.
Turns out those rhizomes had placed little tubers all over the place, ready to colonize.
By this time, I had seeded the circle garden with native plants, and while sunchokes are technically a native, I didn’t want them to dominate this area like they were clearly prepared to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you fight a sunchoke infestation?
It’s not easy, but it’s possible.
Mowing is an option, but it would have to be done very regularly to be effective—the sunchokes didn’t mind being cut back and would quickly regrow.
Mulching would probably work, but I suspect it would have to be a very impenetrable layer to foil these vigorous plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose a war of attrition, making frequent patrols throughout the summer to pull up every sunchoke plant I found in the area.
More would sprout, and a week later I’d pull them up again.
When I had time, I’d also use a trowel to dig out the tubers themselves so they couldn’t just send up a new stem.
This strategy did eventually work, but it took a whole summer of regular attention before I got things under control.
I probably spent more time on this than on all the other weeding I’ve done in this garden in its whole existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I didn’t let this ordeal put me off of growing sunchokes, and I have since planted some elsewhere that are now one of my favorite and most productive crops.
You should consider growing sunchokes too, but learn from my mistakes: grow a named cultivar, and situate it somewhere that is easy to control the spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/sunchokes-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/sunchokes-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/sunchokes-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/sunchokes-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/sunchokes.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Me, later, with some better-behaved sunchokes.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retirement&quot;&gt;Retirement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 2018 growing season, I had established a large permanent vegetable garden elsewhere in the yard and no longer needed the circle space for food.
So now what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t (and still don’t) have a strong vision for this part of the yard.
It’s on the side of our house and visible from the kitchen window, so Katherine wants something pretty to look at while she washes dishes.
We want a small open area for lounging in the sun, but I had no desire to convert all of it back into grass (I hate grass).
We could eventually want to use this space for something specific, like a playhouse, a picnic table, a… dog palace?
Something.
With the future use a question mark, I didn’t want to plant it up with very permanent stuff like fruit trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I decided to take the path of least resistance.
The grass areas around the circle would remain grass for the moment, and I would plant the circle up with something pretty, rabbit-resistant, and low maintenance.
A native plant prairie seemed like the perfect choice.
It would look nice, it wouldn’t need much care, and since we weren’t using the space for anything else, it would be put to work providing food and habitat for native insects.
With the vegetable garden nearby, it would also provide an enticing hangout spot for predator insects who help control pests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the native plants in the rain garden, I had taken a focused, careful approach, buying starts and laying them out according to a thoughtful design plan.
There was to be none of that here.
I’d put down a bunch of seed and whatever grew, grew.
There were also a few perennial food plants–rhubarb, green onions, and perennial arugula–that I left in place, figuring they could wait until I had some other permanent place to move them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought a packet of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prairiemoon.com/pollinator-palooza-prairie-seed-mix-prairie-moon-nursery.html&quot;&gt;Pollinator Palooza seed mix&lt;/a&gt; from Prairie Moon.
As recommended, I sowed the seeds in early winter, right as one of our first major snowfalls arrived.
Many native seeds need “cold stratification” to break dormancy, so letting them winter in place is the way to achieve that with the least effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spring 2018 was a pretty weird season.
The snow and cold hung around a long time, and then the weather turned on a dime to immediately become hot, dry, summer conditions.
I suspect this wasn’t helpful to the seeds, who didn’t have a cool moist transition period to germinate and start establishing.
The outcome that year did not look very good.
Other than some black-eyed susans, very few native plants showed up and I was concerned that the prairie planting had been a failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-first-year-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The new prairie garden growing mostly grass and weeds&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-first-year-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-first-year-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-first-year-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/prairie-first-year.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The pocket prairie, year one. Not looking too promising.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I didn’t care enough to intervene, and 2019 proved much more successful.
Quite a few more natives appeared and the space started to fill in, making the threat of weeds less pressing.
We got some nice flowers, not only from the robust and ever-adventurous black-eyed susans, but from some more unusual participants like figwort and native pasture thistle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-second-year-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The prairie garden with blooming flowers&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-second-year-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-second-year-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-second-year-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/prairie-second-year.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The pocket prairie, year two. Note the black-eyed susans throughout. On the left is some anise hyssop. The big thing on the right is a native thistle. There are a couple purple coneflowers in there too, and some rogue sunchokes that I hadn't pulled yet. In back is some phlox, not native but I got it from a neighbor and left it there until I figured out what to do with it.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prairie fully arrived in 2020.
It’s now a lush area packed with foliage and flowers and constantly busy with pollinators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;slide&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-third-year-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prairie garden with many blooming flowers&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-third-year-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-third-year-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-third-year-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/prairie-third-year.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The pocket prairie, year three. From left to right: bee balm, pasture thistle, figwort, black-eyed susans, purple coneflower, guara. Also dotted around are some grasses that are probably natives, but grasses are too hard to identify.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/coneflower-butterfly-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A butterfly on a purple coneflower&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/coneflower-butterfly-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/coneflower-butterfly-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/coneflower-butterfly-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/coneflower-butterfly.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Coneflowers seem to be a favorite of butterflies.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/thistle-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A bumblebee on a thistle blossom&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/thistle-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/thistle-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/thistle-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/thistle.jpg 6000w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        This native “pasture thistle” was a surprise hit. It’s a huge and striking plant, and the bees loved the giant blossoms.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/bee-balm-bee-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A bumblebee on a monarda blossom&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/bee-balm-bee-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/bee-balm-bee-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/bee-balm-bee-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/bee-balm-bee.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        It’s called “bee balm” for a reason!
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did virtually no weeding or maintenance on it the entire year, and yet almost every plant I could identify was a native.
It seems that the natives, now fully established, have thoroughly out-competed the weeds.
This was always the plan in theory, but seeing it take place in practice was very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/bee-balm-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/bee-balm-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/bee-balm-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/bee-balm-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/bee-balm.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I realized I had put shockingly little work into establishing this area in general.
I had done a bit of weeding in the first two years, mostly of pesky sow thistle, but really very little time in the grand scheme of things.
The only major time investment was fighting back sunchokes, a problem of my own making.
I was probably helped somewhat by not having major weed pressure to begin with, but still, this result feels like a big win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/coneflower-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/coneflower-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/coneflower-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/coneflower.jpg 1200w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty bucks and some patience got me an area that doesn’t need mowing, looks pretty, and provides a huge boost of biodiversity.
The wild and slightly unruly nature of it wouldn’t work in every situation (this year, notably, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prairiemoon.com/gaura-biennis-biennial-gaura-prairie-moon-nursery.html&quot;&gt;gaura&lt;/a&gt; grew about 7 feet tall and then epically flopped over), but in this spot it works great.
Also, the dog likes to bushwhack through this area for no obvious reason.
I swear part of the appeal for her is that if she gets into the middle, the plants are thick enough she’s completely hidden from sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-dog-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dog sitting in the prairie garden&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-dog-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-dog-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/prairie-dog-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/prairie-dog.jpg 1478w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Dog approved.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whirligig&quot;&gt;Whirligig&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a year, Katherine travels to rural Wisconsin to attend a barn dance.
On her way there, she passes &lt;a href=&quot;http://cottagegardenfarm.com/&quot;&gt;a garden store&lt;/a&gt; that is known in the area for making outstanding whirligigs.
Seriously.
You probably thought all whirligigs were about the same quality, but that’s just because you’ve never encountered a truly exemplary whirligig before.
These ones spin effortlessly and come with a lifetime rebalancing guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some discussion, we agreed to invest in a whirligig, so on her next Wisconsin trip Katherine brought one home.
We didn’t have a specific spot in mind for it, but we tried it out in the prairie area and thought it fit in very nicely, so it lives there now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/whirligig-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The whirligig in the middle of the prairie garden&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/whirligig-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/whirligig-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/whirligig-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/whirligig.jpg 1561w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only issue we have is that suicidal figwort plants keep trying to grow directly into the spinning blades and get all chewed up, so we have to keep trimming them back.
We even moved it to a different spot and somehow a new figwort appeared and dove right into the blades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/figwort-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A closeup up figwort flowers&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/figwort-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/resized/figwort-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-first-year-garden/figwort.jpg 1200w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        “I crave death!”
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, it’s a great whirligig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plant-list-first-year&quot;&gt;Plant List (first year)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peas, “Dwarf Gray Sugar”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arugula “Sylvetta”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mesclun Mix&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lettuce, “Amish Deer Tongue”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sunchokes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tomato, “Paul Robeson”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tomato, “Cherokee Purple”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tomato, “Cosmic Eclipse”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tomato, “Iglehart Yellow”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tomato, “Black Cherry”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tomato, “Roma”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sweet Pepper, “King of the North”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sweet Pepper, “Yellow Monster”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pole Bean, “Kentucky Wonder”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scallions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basil, “Herb Emily”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rosemary, “Mozart”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dill, “Dukat”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dill, “Tetra”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cilantro&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thyme, English&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peppermint&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zinnia, “Benary’s Giant Wine”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marigolds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prairie Smoke&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plant-list-wildflowers&quot;&gt;Plant List (wildflowers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wildflowers I’ve positively identified from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prairiemoon.com/pollinator-palooza-prairie-seed-mix-prairie-moon-nursery.html&quot;&gt;the seed mix&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Agastache foeniculum (Anise Hyssop)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baptisia alba (White Wild Indigo)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chamaecrista fasciculata (Partridge Pea)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cirsium discolor (Pasture Thistle)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coreopsis lanceolata (Lance-leaf Coreopsis)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Echinacea purpurea (Purple Coneflower)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gaura longiflora (Large-flowered Gaura)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monarda fistulosa (Wild Bergamot)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Penstemon digitalis (Foxglove Beardtongue)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rudbeckia hirta (Black-eyed Susan)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scrophularia lanceolata (Early Figwort)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time--materials&quot;&gt;Time &amp;amp; Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary cost&quot;&gt;&lt;caption class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Expenses &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal-heading&quot;&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Vegetable garden &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Plants
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$35 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Straw bale
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$11 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twomikes.net/&quot;&gt;Cod juice fertilizer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$8 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Chicken wire and t-posts
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;free &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Salvaged planks
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;free &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$54 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal-heading&quot;&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Native prairie &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prairiemoon.com/pollinator-palooza-prairie-seed-mix-prairie-moon-nursery.html&quot;&gt;Pollinator Palooza seed mix&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$29 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Whirligig
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$140 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$170 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary time&quot;&gt;&lt;caption class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Time &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal-heading&quot;&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Vegetable garden &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Prep
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~4 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Planting
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~4 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Maintenance
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~1 hour per week &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal-heading&quot;&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Native prairie &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Seeding
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~1 hour &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Sunchoke infestation
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~12 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;First year (weeding, mowing)
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~6 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Second year (weeding)
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~4 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Third year (weeding)
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~1 hour &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Garden" /><summary type="html">I had maintained a small garden at both of the last two places we rented, so now that we had a place of our own I was excited to get a garden going. However, we closed on the house at the end of April, and were consumed with moving and some of the more pressing move-in issues after that. The timeline meant that I wasn’t going to have time to do almost any prep work before planting time rolled around.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basement Egress</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/basement-egress.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basement Egress" /><published>2020-11-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/basement-egress</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/basement-egress.html">&lt;p&gt;The basement was mostly finished when we bought the house.
It still needs drywall and ceiling and a few other finishing touches, but it was already waterproofed, insulated, and had a new cement floor with in-floor hydronic heat.
Time will tell if we actually take advantage of it being finished or continue to use it as a basement, like we’re doing now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ready it for use as a finished space, the final important component was an egress window.
This would allow us to have a legal bedroom down there, which is what would give the biggest boost to our property values or whatever.
Beyond looking good on paper, an egress window provides straightforward functional benefits.
It brings a lot more light into the space and makes it feel more like a room and less like a dark basement.
It also gives you a way to escape in case of fire, which is sort of the whole point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of immediate impact on our life, an egress window wasn’t at the top of the priority list.
However, we knew that given the nature of the project we’d make it easier on ourselves if we got it done soon.
Bringing digging machinery into the yard would become more difficult once we had a full fence, and the work itself would be likely to damage any landscaping around the site.
Since a fence and major landscaping were both in the cards for the coming year, it seemed prudent to get our hardscaping out of the way while it was still simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two candidate windows along the north wall of the basement.
They are both framed out as if the original intent was to convert them to egress windows.
We thought about doing both, but that would have doubled the cost and not doubled the benefits.
A single egress window seemed like the best balance for our needs.
One of the windows was situated in a more likely spot for a future bedroom, plus it was a simpler section of wall (the other window sits in a bump-out where the first floor bay window follows down into the foundation), so it got the nod.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;slide&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-outside-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of house exterior showing old basement window&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-outside-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-outside-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-outside-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/before-outside.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The window to be replaced, from the outside.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-close-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup photo of old basement window&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-close-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-close-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-close-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/before-close.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Sad and small.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-inside-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of basement interior showing old basement window&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-inside-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-inside-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/before-inside-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/before-inside.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The window to be replaced, complete with sad curtain behind the vapor barrier. Yes, the basement really is bathed in pink light, that's just how we choose to live.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a couple quotes but didn’t look very hard because &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.egresswindowguy.com/&quot;&gt;Egress Window Guy&lt;/a&gt; seemed like an easy choice.
They get a lot of good reviews on Nextdoor and Angie’s List.
They specialize in this one thing so the whole planning and quoting process is very streamlined.
Their prices are reasonable, and better yet, they have a standardized price sheet for all their options so I was able to get a very straightforward apples-to-apples comparison on the cost differences between various options.
Also, they offer a discount if you obtain an online quote by filling out a questionnaire and sending photos so they can save a site visit.
My kind of people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the effort that goes into an egress window isn’t the window itself, it’s digging a big old hole in the ground for the egress.
It was a two person operation: they brought in a mini-excavator and two wheelbarrows and one person operated the scoop while the other basically ran back and forth carrying loads of dirt to the area I had designated.
He’d run one wheelbarrow to the dirt pile while the other one was being filled, then run it back, swap for the full one, and start again.
That guy must sleep well at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a six-foot hole dug in your yard is a good opportunity to learn about the soil profile.
Once I showed interest, the guy doing the digging helpfully told me about what he had noticed.
Apparently we have a couple feet of good topsoil, then a heavy clay layer, then underneath that is fairly sandy subsoil.
Weird, but not too bad.
This was timely information as well, since I was very shortly installing a rain garden in the same side of the lawn.
In the end we get good enough drainage through the clay layer that I haven’t needed to do anything special, but if our rain garden wasn’t draining quickly, I would have considered trying to dig or punch holes through the clay, knowing that there was well-draining sand underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/in-progress-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The crew working on the window with the hole dug and excavator in the background&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/in-progress-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/in-progress-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/in-progress-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/in-progress.jpg 1205w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Getting the hole ready. This isn't even most of the dirt; note the trodden path leading away from it.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the hole was dug, it was just a matter of sawing through the concrete block foundation and installing a window opening.
I was busy with other stuff so I didn’t pay a lot of attention to this part, but they moved pretty fast.
The whole thing took about two thirds of a work day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was glad we made the decision to do this piece early, because it was somewhat disruptive to the site, as expected.
The crew was very respectful and did their best not to mess up the surrounding area, but digging a big hole is always going to create a bit of havoc.
It didn’t help that the ground still had melting snow on it (thanks, April of Endless Winter).
The mini-excavator left some tracks driving in, and the path used by the beleaguered wheelbarrow shuttle-man got pretty trampled and compacted.
If I already had nice landscaping in the area they were working, I would have been stressed out by this project.
As it was, the whole area was just crappy grass that was due to be torn up and converted shortly anyhow, so I didn’t mind at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t pay extra to have the dirt disposed of, so we were left with a small mountain on our back patio.
A lesson I’ve learned a couple times now: you’re always going to generate way more dirt than you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/dirt-pile-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of a very large pile of dirt&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/dirt-pile-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/dirt-pile-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/dirt-pile-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/dirt-pile.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did eventually relocate it all to other places around the yard, but it took us most of a year to slowly chip away at it.
I had planned to use the dirt to regrade a section of the yard near the foundation, but that didn’t make nearly as big a dent as I had expected.
A lot of it went to leveling out a low spot  in the back yard, and some more went to slightly raising the profile of the new planting areas I put in along the fence in back.
The clay subsoil was the hardest thing to use up, as it was heavy enough to not perform well in planting beds.
That eventually led to the creation of &lt;a href=&quot;/the-mud-head.html&quot;&gt;my great ephemeral masterpiece&lt;/a&gt;, so I guess I just needed to take the whole journey to reach the destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finished window looks very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-outside-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the finished egress window&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-outside-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-outside-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/after-outside.jpg 1200w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember the details of the window options but we got an Anderson 400 Series, I believe because it was a step up from the basic option and my research suggested it would do an acceptable job.
We splashed out for the more spendy timber lining on the well itself instead of a basic galvanized metal sheet.
I’m very glad we did, even though it raised the price considerably.
A window with a galvanized well would be &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt; and would do the job adequately, but I don’t think it would actually make the room better.
The timber well is attractive enough that the window becomes an asset and really adds to the ambiance of the room.
It’s also much prettier from the outside.
Galvanized wells are always a little funky and tend to feel like something you want to screen, while this one serves as a feature in the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-landscape-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the egress window with surrounding landscaping&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-landscape-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-landscape-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-landscape-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/after-landscape.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The timber well meshes wonderfully with the new landscaping.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wider opening also lets in more light and gives a feeling of expansiveness from inside.
This part of the basement feels a lot cheerier than it did with the small dim window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-inside-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the new window from inside, without trim&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-inside-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-inside-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/after-inside.jpg 1200w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the window installed, the only thing left for me to do was finish the interior trim, so I got right to work.
Ha ha!
Just kidding, it’s been three years and I haven’t touched it.
I only took the stickers off the window just now to take this photo.
When we finish the rest of the basement, we’ll finish the window interior.
Until then, it just isn’t a priority.
It’s still the best-looking part of the basement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-inside-wide-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the new window surrounded by unfinished basement and shelving&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-inside-wide-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-inside-wide-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/resized/after-inside-wide-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/basement-egress/after-inside-wide.jpg 1600w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Shhhh, this is fine.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time--materials&quot;&gt;Time &amp;amp; Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary cost &quot;&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal-heading&quot;&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Contractor Expenses &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Base price (materials &amp;amp; labor)
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$1,620 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Upgrade to timber well
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$630 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Permit
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$75 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;total&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$2,325 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Basement" /><category term="Exterior" /><category term="Contractors" /><category term="Not a lot of finish" /><summary type="html">The basement was mostly finished when we bought the house. It still needs drywall and ceiling and a few other finishing touches, but it was already waterproofed, insulated, and had a new cement floor with in-floor hydronic heat. Time will tell if we actually take advantage of it being finished or continue to use it as a basement, like we’re doing now.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Chimney</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/the-chimney.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Chimney" /><published>2020-08-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/the-chimney</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/the-chimney.html">&lt;p&gt;A recurring theme of this journal is going to be a comment our inspector made concerning the previous owners of our house: “they had a lot of &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; in them, but not a lot of &lt;em&gt;finish&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the many partially-completed projects we inherited when we bought the house was the fireplace and chimney.
The previous owners had installed a nice new fireplace and judging by the soot buildup, they had enjoyed it frequently.
One problem: they never finished the chimney.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/inspection-1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;Page of the inspection report detailing issues with chimney&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/inspection-480.png 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/inspection-800.png 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/inspection-1200.png 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/inspection.png 1950w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Shoutout to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.structuretech.com/&quot;&gt;Structure Tech&lt;/a&gt; for their great inspection work.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This being a fancy new fireplace, the exhaust vents through a double- or triple-walled aluminum stovepipe rather than a traditional opening.
The actual chimney part is just for structure and looks.
It’s wood framing clad with plywood and tar paper and finished with something weatherproof and decorative.
Only the previous owners never made it to “finished” and just left it at plywood and tar paper instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looked pretty bad, obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/before-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the chimney clad in tar paper&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/before-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/before-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/before-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/before.jpg 3984w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also had functional concerns: the tar paper is a moisture shield but there’s no real guarantee that it will be effective if it has to do all the work itself.
Getting moisture under the tar paper, rotting the plywood and entering the rest of the house seemed like a recipe for a bad time.
The chimney was high on our priority list for these reasons, but the final straw was when a woodpecker started visiting daily to peck at the chimney.
It felt like it was mocking us for our shortcomings and portending worse problems in the future.
&lt;em&gt;I GET IT, WOODPECKER, WE SHOULD HAVE COVERED THIS UP BY NOW!&lt;/em&gt;
After a week of being blatantly taunted by a bird, I resolved to finish the chimney once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was relatively sure I knew what we needed.
The structural parts of the chimney were all there, we just needed to cover it with something that provided permanent weatherproofing and looked like an actual finished product.
Apparently it’s common to put siding on these types of chimneys (because the outer structure doesn’t actually experience much heat), but I was never convinced that we could pull that off in a way that was anything but ugly.
The chimney is quite tall, presumably because it needs to extend beyond the second floor, and it comes directly out of the roof so it doesn’t have any visual connection to the rest of the exterior walls.
Turning it into a weird pillar of siding seemed like a great way to call attention to how awkward it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/mockup-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A mockup of the chimney with matching siding&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/mockup-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/mockup-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/mockup-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/mockup.jpg 2824w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        A mockup. See? It's weird.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous owners had planned to do river stone to match the fireplace finish, but we are not that into river stone and besides, it wouldn’t fit the style of the neighborhood at all.
Longfellow is a lot of old houses and of those that still have visible chimney elements, it’s a split of about 90% red brick and 10% yellow brick.
Brick seemed like the easy choice, if we could make it work.
Some research led me to “thin brick”, which is thin slices of brick face that get attached to a backing element like, say, the structural column of a modern chimney.
Thin brick is still true brick material and still gets mortared in, so it reportedly has durability comparable to actual brick.
It doesn’t have the immense weight of full brick, so it doesn’t require the support structure that a traditional masonry chimney would.
Seemed like we had a winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding someone to actually do the job proved much more difficult.
Chimney companies told me I should find a mason.
Masons told me they didn’t do veneers.
Contractors told me I should put siding on it.
Siding companies told me they only did full-house jobs.
The city inspector told me I needed to have it inspected because he didn’t think it was to code (it was).
The overall hassle of finding someone who wanted to do the job felt very disproportionate to the actual size of the job. Welcome to home ownership, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After not seeing much success through other routes, I decided to give &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thumbtack.com/&quot;&gt;Thumbtack&lt;/a&gt; a try and it worked out well for me (they have since changed their business model so I wouldn’t necessarily vouch for them any more).
We got matched up with several worthwhile contractors, including the one we went with, Ryan at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.creativeconceptsconcrete.com/&quot;&gt;Creative Concepts&lt;/a&gt;.
Ryan not only had the best quoting process and communication, his bid came in well under all the others, so it ended up being an easy decision.
I suspect Ryan may have underbid the job and regretted it later, but if that was the case he was a total professional about it and never turned it into my problem.
He and his crew did great work and (as far as my untrained eyes can tell) the results are excellent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lined the job up to be part of our spring of construction, hoping that we could get the chimney folks done and out of the way before the egress window and fence folks started.
It worked out in the end, though it wasn’t quite as simple as any of us hoped.
The installation was, in theory, a pretty straightforward affair.
Erect scaffolding, check the existing structure and put up metal lathing.
The tar paper had done an admirable job protecting the structure from the elements, so the crew replaced it but was able to leave the wood structure untouched.
After an inspector checked it, they’d spend a couple days brick &amp;amp; mortaring and we’d be all done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/in-progress-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A worker halfway through laying bricks&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/in-progress-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/in-progress-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/in-progress-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/in-progress.jpg 3024w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        April 12th. This was the last of the work that happened for a while.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, winter decided to perform a Minnesota goodbye that year.
The poor crew had a snowstorm roll in halfway through the bricklaying, and the temperature dropped enough that they couldn’t keep putting up mortar because it wouldn’t cure properly.
So work got suspended for over a week while April refused to act like spring.
Ryan was very communicative and kept apologizing for the delays, which I appreciated, but it’s not like I expected him to be able control the weather.
These things happen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/dog-in-snow-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Rigby the dog in deep snow&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/dog-in-snow-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/dog-in-snow-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/dog-in-snow-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/dog-in-snow.jpg 3024w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        April 15th, 2018.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These delays would have messed up the scheduling with the other contractors, but the cold was causing delays for everything else too, so it worked out okay.
The egress window had to wait until there wasn’t feet of snow on the ground, and our fence builder couldn’t start until the ground thawed, so everything ended up happening in the original order, just several weeks late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/dog-at-window-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Rigby the dog watching snow outside the window with construction scaffolding in the background&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/dog-at-window-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/dog-at-window-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/dog-at-window-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/dog-at-window.jpg 3338w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the weather cleared, the crew wrapped up the rest of the work pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide&quot; data-splide=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;slide&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;splide__track&quot;&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;splide__list&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/chimney-bottom-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the finished chimney&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/chimney-bottom-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/chimney-bottom-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/chimney-bottom-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/chimney-bottom.jpg 3036w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        There are more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hebronbrick.com/products/thin-brick/&quot;&gt;color options&lt;/a&gt; than you might expect. We went with &quot;Bell Tower&quot;, or as I like to call it, &quot;Brick&quot;.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/chimney-top-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the finished chimney&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/chimney-top-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/chimney-top-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/chimney-top-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/chimney-top.jpg 2898w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        View from the attic window
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image splide__slide&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/house-finished-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the house with finished chimney&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/house-finished-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/house-finished-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/house-finished-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/house-finished.jpg 5877w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that the chimney looks like brick, that it fits the style of our house and fits the style of the neighborhood.
It doesn’t draw attention to itself any more and that was exactly the goal.
Most of all, I like that I just won’t think about it very often.
If it’s as durable as promised, I should have decades before it needs any attention, and the freedom to spend less time worrying about my chimney is a worthy investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finishing your chimney: would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/fireplace-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of a fire in the fireplace&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/fireplace-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/fireplace-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/resized/fireplace-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-chimney/fireplace.jpg 4048w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time--materials&quot;&gt;Time &amp;amp; Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary cost &quot;&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;subtotal-heading&quot;&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Contractor Expenses &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Materials: Lath, weep, masonry, sakcrete, thin brick
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$1,560 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Labor: Scaffolding
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$250 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Labor: Installation
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$1,700 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Equipment &amp;amp; truck
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$300 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Permit
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$200 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;total&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$4,010 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Exterior" /><category term="Contractors" /><category term="Not a lot of finish" /><summary type="html">A recurring theme of this journal is going to be a comment our inspector made concerning the previous owners of our house: “they had a lot of start in them, but not a lot of finish.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Garage</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/2019/06/20/the-garage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Garage" /><published>2019-06-20T09:57:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-06-20T09:57:00-05:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/2019/06/20/the-garage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/2019/06/20/the-garage.html">&lt;p&gt;We’ll start this blog with the first true project we tackled after moving in: the garage.
This was an obvious place for us to start because it felt like a very doable entry point, and because it was pretty urgent. Why? Let’s review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/exterior-view-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the garage exterior&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/exterior-view-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/exterior-view-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/exterior-view-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/exterior-view.jpg 6016w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The garage is… not in great shape.
It’s as old as the house and not built with the same sort of care as the house.
The framing sits directly on the ground, and after a hundred years of ground contact, the wood is in pretty bad shape!
Due to this slow loss of structural integrity, the whole thing has a pretty noticeable lean to it.
We’ll come back to that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the structural issues, a previous owner had converted a third of the garage into the grimiest of hangout caves.
Plastic sheeting had been hung to create a room of sorts and the walls had been partly insulated (more on that in a moment).
When we toured, the space was still furnished with a couch, recliner, TV and stereo system, and most concerningly, a wood-burning stove.
Truly a four-season hidey-hole.
Part of me perversely hoped they would leave behind the stove, but by the time we closed it was gone with only the patched chimney hole to mark where it had been.
Probably worth good money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had a photo of the cave in its full glory as it was truly a sight to behold.
Even photos, though, wouldn’t capture to most distinctive feature of the garage as we got it: the smell.
It reeked overpoweringly of cigarette smoke.
The smell was so potent I found it truly difficult to spend more than a few seconds in the garage.
I would gulp a big breath a few feet from the door and try to hold it until I had gotten what I needed and retreated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We needed to be able to use the garage, so we needed to address the smell and general grossness.
Our best bet seemed to be stripping it as much as we could.
The weird slapdash shelves had to go.
The haphazard light fixture in the back had to go.
And most importantly, the very handmade and smoke-impregnated insulation had to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demo-day&quot;&gt;Demo day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We visited the hardware store for a few basic supplies to prepare: dust masks, trash bags, and most crucially, the biggest crowbar I could find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/crowbar-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A very large crowbar&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/crowbar-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/crowbar-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/crowbar-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/crowbar.jpg 3508w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        This was an excellent purchase.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most expendable clothing worn, gear donned. It was time, as Monty Don would put it, “to get stuck in”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/katherine-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Katherine with safety gear working on demo in the garage&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/katherine-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/katherine-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/katherine-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/katherine.jpg 3024w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first surprise was that the wall insulation was entirely wood shavings.
It looked like someone with a woodworking hobby had spent some unfathomable number of years collecting the dust and planer shavings and pouring them into the walls.
Kind of impressive, but I’d also prefer a structure that isn’t ready to turn into Minneapolis’ biggest bonfire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/insulation-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A removed wall panel with wood shaving insulation behind it&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/insulation-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/insulation-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/insulation-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/insulation.jpg 3894w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Cool. Cool cool cool.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of our time was spent prying off the old planks holding the insulation in and bagging up the wood shavings.
The planks I saved and used for temporary garden paths and other scrap purposes.
The wood shavings we put on Craigslist and were quickly collected by some nice folks excited to mulch a strawberry bed with them.
I probably could have saved them for my own garden, but I was so disgusted by the whole deal that I just wanted them gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an extra fun surprise, some of the insulated sections contained interesting items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/knives-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Two old knives&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/knives-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/knives-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/knives.jpg 1080w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two knives buried in the shavings.
I’d give it a 40% probability that at least one of these was used in a murder, because why else would you hide knives in the walls of a garage?!
The big one is a nice form factor for stabbing into a wood surface.
For some reason it annoys Katherine when I leave it like this, so I took to periodically moving it to a different stud in the garage just to keep her on her toes.
I suspect she has recently confiscated it and hidden it from me.
I’ll find it, though.
&lt;em&gt;I’ll find it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/wtf-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A patch of fur with a leather strap&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/wtf-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/wtf-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/wtf.jpg 1080w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also this horrifying patch of… fur and leather?
I cannot imagine what this is and I have made a point not to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only things we kept were the shop lights mounted to the rafters and a battered but sturdy workbench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the siding and shelves removed, we pulled most of the stray nails out of the walls, swept out a decade of rubble and cigarette ash, and left the garage door open for a couple days.
It worked!
The cigarette smell went from overpowering to simply noticeable, and it has since faded completely.
Our garage was clear and relatively clean, and we could start using it for our own stuff.
If I were smart I would have taken a photo of it at this stage to illustrate for you our perfect minimalist lifestyle.
I am not, and we immediately filled it with disorganized piles of our own junk, something which we have still not fully gotten back under control two years later.
Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/mess-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A very messy section of the garage&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/mess-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/mess-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/mess-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/mess.jpg 3704w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The mess of shame.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changing-the-open-door-policy&quot;&gt;Changing the open-door policy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we put anything of value in the garage, though, there was one more issue to address.
The service door was what I would describe as “not a real door”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/old_door-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The old door on the garage&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/old_door-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/old_door-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/old_door-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/old_door.jpg 4032w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was definitely an interior door that someone had repurposed at some point.
The hinges were on the outside, which would be a security problem if not for the fact that the locking latch was so tenuously attached that I think I probably could have compromised it with my bare hands.
Garage break-ins are enough of a problem in South Minneapolis that I did not want to be the easiest garage on the block to break into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was going to be a project, though.
The door frame was a weird nonstandard size that no door would fit.
And remember that lean?
Turns out an important tenet of hanging doors is to try to do it on something that is relatively plumb and square.
This opening was neither.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was time to call for backup, namely Jeff my handy father-in-law and his Sawzall.
He advised that we buy a standard door and alter the opening to fit, so I found the cheapest metal security door that looked decent, strapped it to the roof of the car in the always-eerily-abandoned parking lot of the West St. Paul Lowes, and drove it home.
Jeff came over for a long Saturday in which we pulled out some of the existing framing, cut a larger opening in the siding, added new studs and support beams, and installed the door.
It was a precision operation to get it in a place where it would clear both the concrete floor of the garage and the overhead rails for the automatic garage door.
After a lot of adjusting and checking and adjusting some more, we got it in and attached and to my great relief, it works well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/new_door_interior-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The new door viewed from the garage interior&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/new_door_interior-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/new_door_interior-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/new_door_interior-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/new_door_interior.jpg 4016w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        New door, new studs.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that it isn’t without its quirks.
Remember how I told you about the garage’s pronounced lean?
We had a decision on whether to install the door square with the rest of the garage, or plumb with the actual ground.
We chose plumb, and I am entirely confident this was the right decision, but this does mean that the door is very obviously out of alignment with the rest of the garage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/new_door-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The new door installed in the garage, which is noticeably not aligned with the windows or roofline&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/new_door-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/new_door-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/new_door-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/new_door.jpg 4018w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        This is not an optical illusion. That's… just how it is.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the door there really accentuates just how much the rest of the structure is listing.
It’s fine.
I’m sure it’s totally fine.
Nothing to worry about here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime later, I finally got around to installing some trim that I bought from our local salvage shop.
It looks okay.
Go me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/trim-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The new door with exterior trim&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/trim-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/trim-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/trim-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/trim.jpg 2265w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also eventually installed a security light in place of the old lamp that had been on that electrical box, but it is such an utter hack job that I’m not even going to document it.
It’s nice to have a proper light there, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organization&quot;&gt;Organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be working on organizing the garage for the rest of our lives, plus or minus a couple years.
We’ve made some progress, at least, which I will share with you in the spirit of incremental good-enough-ism that permeates this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought some 4’x8’ sections of the cheapest pegboard and transported them precariously home on the roof of our Subaru.
Next time just buy the 4’x4’ sections, Ian you dummy.
Those would be way easier to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I screwed one panel to the studs on each side of the garage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/pegboard_with_cutouts-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pegboard with cutouts for the window and outlet box&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/pegboard_with_cutouts-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/pegboard_with_cutouts-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/pegboard_with_cutouts-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/pegboard_with_cutouts.jpg 4048w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Notice the crowbar presiding over its domain.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one went right over the window and electrical box because I was far too lazy to measure and cut out holes prior to attaching it.
Two years later, after purchasing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dremel.com/en_US/products/-/show-product/tools/multi-max-mm50&quot;&gt;an oscillating multi-tool&lt;/a&gt;, I finally got around to cutting these out, totally professionally!
This one will probably hold workshop tools, at whatever future date I dig out and organize the workbench so I can use that area as an actual workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other side holds gardening tools and a few other yard items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/garden_pegboard-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pegboard garden implements on pegs&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/garden_pegboard-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/garden_pegboard-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/garden_pegboard-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/garden_pegboard.jpg 3884w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I feel prouder of my organization on the near side of this one.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started out with this tool rack that my father has been storing in the basement (in original packaging) for presumably several decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/old_tool_rack-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Large garden tools on hanging rack&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/old_tool_rack-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/old_tool_rack-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/old_tool_rack-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/old_tool_rack.jpg 3484w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helped a lot to corral all the larger implements in one place, but the hooks on the rack didn’t work for everything, and it was bending considerably under all the weight.
I looked around and found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.homedepot.com/p/Everbilt-36-in-80-lb-Aluminum-8-Clamp-Wall-Rack-Organizer-18021/202305428&quot;&gt;a rack at Home Depot&lt;/a&gt; that looked decent and was cheap.
One problem: it’s drilled for standard 16” studs, and in the garage the studs are 24” for whatever reason.
Am I going to let that stop me?
Heck no!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tool_rack_drilled-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New hole drilled in the rack&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tool_rack_drilled-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tool_rack_drilled-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tool_rack_drilled-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/tool_rack_drilled.jpg 3385w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just drill a new hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tool_rack-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New tool rack with tools mounted&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tool_rack-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tool_rack-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tool_rack-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/tool_rack.jpg 3036w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Rack mounted, plus some storage hooks and strategically placed nails for the other tools.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new rack seems sturdy and the gripper mechanisms hold the tools well.
Hopefully it will hold up over time, but even if it doesn’t, it was cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/storage_shelf-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A large metal storage shelf&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/storage_shelf-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/storage_shelf-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/storage_shelf-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/storage_shelf.jpg 3036w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Costco’s version of your classic metal storage shelf, and like everything from Costco they are 30% larger than the standard version.
Luckily they just barely fit in the space, and give us a lot of space for miscellany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tire_hooks-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Storage hooks holding tires and shovels&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tire_hooks-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tire_hooks-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tire_hooks-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/tire_hooks.jpg 4048w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hooks on the walls hold bike tires, hoses, and cords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/cord_hooks-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Storage hooks holding extension cords&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/cord_hooks-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/cord_hooks-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/cord_hooks-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/cord_hooks.jpg 3036w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.studgrabbers.com/&quot;&gt;these awesome stud-grabbing hooks&lt;/a&gt; from the Grandstand at the State Fair, and I didn’t even mind paying Grandstand pricing because they are so darn nifty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/bike_rack-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Freestanding bike racks&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/bike_rack-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/bike_rack-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/bike_rack-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/bike_rack.jpg 2886w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our everyday-use bikes go in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Feedback-Sports-Bicycle-Storage-Stand/dp/B006JXYGW0&quot;&gt;these lovely Feedback Sports stands&lt;/a&gt; we’ve had for years.
The front of the garage hosts the most frequently-accessed items, like the bikes, tools, wheelbarrow, and lawn mower.
The back of the garage is a dark tangled forest of chicken wire and scrap wood.
I don’t go back there any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tandem-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tandem bike hanging from ceiling hoist&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tandem-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tandem-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/tandem-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/tandem.jpg 3036w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We acquired a tandem bike from a family member, which seemed like the perfect use for a bike hoist I had picked up years earlier.
I screwed up some 2x4 supports to mount that to the rafters.
The bike hangs and our bike trailers and lawn mowers go on the floor under and around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thats-it-for-now&quot;&gt;That’s it for now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someday this garage will lean a little too far and fall over.
We’re hoping that’s a few decades out still, but who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/branch-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A fallen tree branch that landed on the garage&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/branch-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/branch-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/branch-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/branch.jpg 4032w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        This branch tried to kill the garage. It did not succeed.
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, it’s certainly not a perfect space but it’s good enough, and I’m happy that we’ve made it functional for our lives with only a very small investment of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sides of the entrance had a bunch of random auto parts stickers.
I scraped all of them off with a putty knife except for this Pabst one, which I think I’ll leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/pbr-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An old Budweiser sticker&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/pbr-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/pbr-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/resized/pbr-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/the-garage/pbr.jpg 6016w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that I actually like PBR (gustatorily &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; ideologically), but I like that it is legitimately vintage at this point, and it serves as a very small reminder of what this garage has seen, and of the weird chain-smoker who loved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time--materials&quot;&gt;Time &amp;amp; Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary time &quot;&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Demo
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~15 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Door install
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~15 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Organization
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;several lifetimes &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;total&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~30 hours &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary cost &quot;&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Crowbar
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$15 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Dust masks
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$5 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Security door
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$110 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Doorknob and lock kit
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$40 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Pegboard and accessories
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$20 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Bike hoist
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;owned &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Storage shelves (2)
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$120 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Tool rack
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$18 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Nifty hooks
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$20 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;total&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$350 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We’ll start this blog with the first true project we tackled after moving in: the garage. This was an obvious place for us to start because it felt like a very doable entry point, and because it was pretty urgent. Why? Let’s review.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What to expect from this blog</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/2018/12/13/what-to-expect.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What to expect from this blog" /><published>2018-12-13T10:13:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-12-13T10:13:00-06:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/2018/12/13/what-to-expect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/2018/12/13/what-to-expect.html">&lt;p&gt;This is as much my personal house journal as it is a public blog.
I’ll try to keep it interesting, but if you’re expecting a lot of polish, you’re probably in the wrong place.
In order for this thing to work, I need to keep posting to it.
The only way that’s going to happen is if I establish an achievable bar for myself and the amount of time I have available to me: no masterpieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most photos will be taken in the midst of the project, with whatever camera I have at hand, with a minimum of staging, in whatever lighting conditions are easily available.
In other words, they won’t be perfect.
If you’re expecting the gorgeous visual record of, say, &lt;a href=&quot;https://projectpalermo.com/&quot;&gt;Project Palermo&lt;/a&gt;, you’re going to be disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/palermo_kitchen_island-800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Project Palermo's beautiful kitchen&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/palermo_kitchen_island-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/palermo_kitchen_island-800.jpg 800w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/palermo_kitchen_island.jpg 1200w&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        It won't look like this.
        
          &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://projectpalermo.com/bungalow-tour/&quot;&gt;Project Palermo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also practical people, and are focused on making functional changes that improve the house and make it a better fit for our lives.
In other words, many of our projects are not all that glamorous.
I lean towards completeness over pizazz, so I intend to write about even the less exciting projects to give a more accurate depiction of what our house project life actually looks like.
It’s not all sledgehammers and shiplap, y’know?
I’ll try to spare you too much boredom, at least, by writing &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; about the interesting stuff and &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; about the boring stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also by no means experts in any aspect of home renovation or landscaping.
I tend to do my research, but that won’t always take the place of many years of experience.
So you won’t be getting expert advice here; it’ll be more like going through the learning process &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; me.
And when I make mistakes, I’ll talk about those too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the--question&quot;&gt;The 💰💰💰 question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing about money, especially in the context of home ownership, is always a little uncomfortable.
I cannot, and probably should not, turn a blind eye to the immense amount of privilege that put us in a position where we can own a nice home in a nice neighborhood in a nice city.
We’re extremely lucky to not only own a home but to have some extra money available to improve it.
Not everyone is so lucky, and there’s no way to embark on this sort of journey without participating in the existing state of economic inequality in this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I don’t think it does anyone any good to dance around the topic.
There’s a lot to be learned by seeing how much someone else pays for what, so I plan to give you the numbers, in as much detail as I can, for most of our projects.
Sometimes you’ll find we pay surprisingly little.
Other times we’ll pay a lot.
When we make financial decisions, I’ll try to talk about how we reached those decisions and what other options were available to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we’re on the subject, we might as well tackle the biggest financial decision of all: the house! Our house cost almost exactly three hundred thousand dollars.
Well, our final accepted offer was $301K, plus we paid closing costs.
We beat out a number of other offers and I’m fairly confident that was only as much as we needed to pay to get the place.
Had we been ready to buy the previous fall when the house sat on the market for a while, we probably could have had it for $289K.
Still, when I look around at our house and yard, I can’t help but feel like we got a steal.
There’s probably a little objective truth to that–the market has only gotten more competitive since then and our house would probably receive more offers and sell for more today.
Mostly, though, it’s a subjective truth.
The house was a steal &lt;em&gt;for us&lt;/em&gt; because it fits us so well, because its strengths are the things that are important to us and its weaknesses are things we don’t mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying a house for the first time is &lt;strong&gt;terrifying&lt;/strong&gt;.
We are not big spenders, and buying a Subaru the year prior had been totally foreign ground to us in terms of purchase size.
Now all of the sudden we were wiring off $75K for a down payment!
The wire transfer process, but the way, is an entirely insane way to process house payments.
The lender very helpfully points out to you that if it goes to the wrong account, they’re probably never getting the money back, so MAKE SURE YOU TYPE THE NUMBERS CORRECTLY, HA HA HA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katherine and I had never carried a notable amount of debt in our lives (see: privilege), so signing off on a 30-year mortgage was frightening as well.
Even worse is the mortgage disclosure (required by law) that informs you how much you will pay in combined principle and interest if you pay back on schedule
😭&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most helpful thing we did to prepare on the money side was that we spent a lot of time thinking about buying a house before we bought a house.
We knew what kind of price ranges were available to us, we knew what sort of down payment and monthly mortgage payments we’d be looking at and what would be comfortable given our existing budget.
That’s not to say we were perfectly prepared; the cost of repairs and maintenance in particular was very hard to get a good prediction for, so we ended up winging it a bit by virtue of having enough cushion of extra cash to absorb a couple unexpected blows.
I would have been more worried about those costs if our house had many issues that urgently needed fixing.
Luckily, almost all the unfinished projects in the house were optional improvements, so we felt comfortable that if we couldn’t afford some of them, they would simply remain unfinished until we could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most good things in life take a combination of good fortune and good choices.
Good fortune: we have sizable savings and income, and the housing market in Minneapolis is not outrageous like many of the West Coast cities.
Good choices: we saved carefully and bought a house later in life, and we don’t cultivate lavish tastes or reach beyond what we can safely afford.
Between these two, our planning was good enough and we aren’t walking a razor’s edge of being able to afford our house.
This in turn opens the door to future possibilities of what we can achieve when we have extra capital to push around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of our good fortune finds us undeserved.
Some of it is just good choices, aged a few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you today with a breakdown of our purchase and moving costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;summary cost &quot;&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;House
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$301,000 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Monthly mortgage payment (including property taxes)
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$1,500 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Down payment (25%)
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$75,250 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Closing costs
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;$7,000 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Inspection
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$800 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;line-item&quot;&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Moving costs
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;amount&quot;&gt;~$350 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Meta" /><summary type="html">This is as much my personal house journal as it is a public blog. I’ll try to keep it interesting, but if you’re expecting a lot of polish, you’re probably in the wrong place. In order for this thing to work, I need to keep posting to it. The only way that’s going to happen is if I establish an achievable bar for myself and the amount of time I have available to me: no masterpieces.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Old House</title><link href="https://house.youngram.com/2018/10/04/our-old-house.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Old House" /><published>2018-10-04T18:07:13-05:00</published><updated>2018-10-04T18:07:13-05:00</updated><id>https://house.youngram.com/2018/10/04/our-old-house</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://house.youngram.com/2018/10/04/our-old-house.html">&lt;p&gt;In April 2017, we became the proud owners of a beautiful old house in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/house_orig_front-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/house_orig_front-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/house_orig_front-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/house_orig_front-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/house_orig_front.jpg 6000w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I see it, we didn’t so much find the house as the house found us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2017, we were starting to &lt;strong&gt;think&lt;/strong&gt; about looking at houses, but we were not yet &lt;strong&gt;looking&lt;/strong&gt; at houses.
We had started a casual preliminary conversation with a realtor (the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thevoreisteam.com/&quot;&gt;Robin Voreis&lt;/a&gt;, who would soon become our official realtor), but no paperwork had been signed and no commitments made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I was out biking through the neighborhood when I passed a “For Sale” sign.
As I glanced over some magnificent evergreens caught my eye, and that was enough to get me to pull over for a closer look.
A good-sized 2.5 story house… double corner lot… lots of sun…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well shoot,&lt;/em&gt; I thought. &lt;em&gt;We better at least take a look.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At home I mentioned it to Katherine and it turned out that she had been trolling online realty listings and had noticed the very same house and was planning to tell me about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well shoot,&lt;/em&gt; I thought. &lt;em&gt;Maybe we better get a showing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I called Robin back and told her that even though two days before I had told her we’d be getting started in “about a month”, the timeline had changed to “right now” and could she please schedule a showing?
Inside was a lot of classic original South Minneapolis trim, no major problems, and just enough flaws to keep it within our price range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well shoot,&lt;/em&gt; we thought. &lt;em&gt;Guess we better put in an offer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then our offer was accepted(!) and it was off to the races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, we bought the first house we looked at.
What can I say?
Love hits when it hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing about this was the house-hunting process I imagined we would have, but I don’t regret a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;single-image&quot;&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/house_sold_sign-1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo&quot; srcset=&quot;
https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/house_sold_sign-480.jpg 480w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/house_sold_sign-800.jpg 800w, https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/resized/house_sold_sign-1200.jpg 1200w, 
 https://house.youngram.com/assets/images/house_sold_sign.jpg 4032w&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll cover the house more in a future post, but for now I’ll leave it there.
Like a birth story, but for our house, and no placentas involved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In April 2017, we became the proud owners of a beautiful old house in Minneapolis.</summary></entry></feed>